Guide to the May Day Rally and Yale Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
May Day Rally and Yale collection
1969-1974
RU 86
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
20.75
(19 boxes, 51 audiocassettes, and 2 film reels.)
The materials consist of correspondence, press releases, oral history transcripts, objects, and printed material documenting Yale student involvement in the 1970 May Day rally in New Haven, Connecticut and published materials collected by the donor as a stringer for the "New York Times" related to Yale's student strike, the anti-war movement, and the Black Panthers trial in New Haven. Also included are publications related to anti-war activities nationally.
Custodial History
Black Panther "solidarity" shirt and silk screen banner gift of Ms. Karla Forsythe, 2013. Films of May Day activities from the New Haven Green gift of Michael Stickrod, 2016.
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 41 (YRG 41), Records documenting student life.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Biographical / Historical
May Day weekend took place May 1-3, 1970 as a rally to protest the murder trial in New Haven of Black Panther party chairman Bobby Seale and seven other party members. Normal academic activities were suspended so that Yale students, faculty, and staff could assist in preparing the campus for the rally. Yale University opened its doors to demonstrators by offering shelter, food, day care, and first aid throughout the weekend. Approximately 15,000 people attended the first day of rallies without significant disruption or disorder. Fewer remained the following days, and academic activities resumed by Monday May 4.
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of correspondence, press releases, oral history transcripts, objects, and printed material documenting Yale student involvement in the 1970 May Day rally in New Haven, Connecticut and published materials collected by the donor as a stringer for the "New York Times" related to Yale's student strike, the anti-war movement, and the Black Panthers trial in New Haven. Also included are publications related to anti-war activities nationally. Some posters and broadsides in Accession 1971-A-004 that were originally located in box 2 are now located in box 6.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession.
General
1917-M-004, box 4, folder "Miscellaneous statements and releases by community groups, New Haven Police Department, and Others" reported missing in 2016.
Student movements; Student protesters; Student strikes; Students -- Political activity; Black Panther Party; Yale University -- Students -- Political activity
- Yale "Movement" Collection, circa 1970-1974; Accession 1971-A-004
  - May Day Strike, 1970
    General
    1917-M-004, box 4, folder "Miscellaneous statements and releases by community groups, New Haven Police Department, and Others" reported missing in 2016.
    - Black Panthers (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
    - Black Panthers - Law students" and family memoranda (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Black Panthers - Periodicals (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    - Strike newspapers, press releases, statements (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Yale Daily News - Clippings and selected issues (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Yale Graduate Professional - Selected issues (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - [Poem] Ginsberg, Allen. May King's Prophecy. [New Haven], May Day Noon 1970. 2 p. (typescript) with stamp (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Legal and medical preparedness circulars (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - New Haven Police Department - memoranda, circulars (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Statements, releases - Kingman Brewster (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Strike Committee - Notes and miscellaneous materials from meetings (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    - Yale Universities News Bureau - Releases (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Posters (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Strike Newspaper (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - Miscellaneous clippings (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous newspapers (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - [Essay] Samuels, Ed. Dear Mom and Dad. An account of Mayday at Yale. New Haven, [1970]. 114 p. (Typescript, electrostatic copy) (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - News releases, leaflets, et cetera, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Statements, releases, et cetera - faculty and administration, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Statements, releases, et cetera - students and others, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
    - Miscellaneous statements and releases by community groups, New Haven Police Dept. and others (Box 4, Folder 1)
      1971-M-004, box 4, folder "Miscellaneous statements and releases by community groups, New Haven Police Department, and Others" reported missing in 2016.
    - National Student Strike - Releases, issues of the newspaper nos. 8, 9, May 12, 14, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Student strikes at other colleges and universities - leaflets, bulletins, etc. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Other controversy at Yale - arranged topically:
      - Gay Liberation (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Labor Unions (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Reserve Officer Training Corps (ROTC), 1969 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Right wing politics (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Shockley and report on Free speech, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Sex and birth control (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Women and co-education (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Yale Institute for Social Sciences - Proposal: student comment and other discussion, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Yale-New Haven relations (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Yale Third World Liberation (organization) (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Lynd, Staughton - Letters of Yale Class of 1926 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Publications distributed at Yale on political issues, ca. 1970, arranged topically:
    - Black Panthers (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Draft resistance (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Ecology (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Peace movement (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Political and economic groups - various protest actions (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Politics - General (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Students for a Democratic Society (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Vietnam (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
    - Miscellaneous protest publications, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Posters and broadsides, 1970, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Press release, correspondence, and paper on Black Power, 1970; Accession 1981-A-064
  - Press release, correspondence, and paper on Black Power, 1970 (Box 1)
- Interviews of people involved in the 1970 May Day Strike, Accession 1983-A-108
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  - Black and Spanish press conference, audiocassette (Box 2)
  - Boell, Edgar, audiocassette (Box 4)
  - Brewster, Kingman, interviewed by David Winn, audiocassette (Box 5)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cannon, Beekman, audiocassette (Box 6)
  - Chauncey, Henry, interviewed by Mr. Solomon, audiocassette (Box 7)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Coffin, Rev. William Sloane, interviewed by Brooke Manville, 1 (Box 8)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cottrol, Bob, interviewed by Brooke Manville, 2 audiocassettes (Box 9–10)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dawson, Ralph, audiocassette (Box 11)
  - Eisenstein, Hester, interviewed by Joel Krieger, 2 audiocassettes (Box 12–13)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Fanton, Jonathan, audiocassette (Box 14)
  - Farley, Bill, audiocassette (Box 15)
  - Fitt, Alfred, audiocassette (Box 16)
  - Griffin, Martin, audiocassette (Box 17)
  - Harvey, G. and Robert Brewster, audiocassette (Box 18)
  - Harowitz, Bill, audiocassette (Box 19)
  - Johnson, Gary and J. Cohen, audiocassette (Box 20)
  - Kagan, Donald, interviewed by Brook Manville, audiocassette (Box 21)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Kegan, Michael, audiocassette (Box 22)
  - Kenniston, K., audiocassette (Box 23)
  - Kernan, Alvin, interviewed by David Winn, audiocassette (Box 24)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lee, Richard and Gerard Swordes, audiocassette (Box 25)
  - Machioni, Al, and Paul Rahe, interviewed by Brooke Manville, 1 (Box 26)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mills, Kenneth, interviewed by John Taft, 2 audiocassettes (Box 27–28)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Morris, James, interviewed by Brook Manville, audiocassette (Box 29–30)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ogilvy, James A., audiocassette (Box 31)
  - Parry, Adam, audiocassette (Box 32)
  - Press conference, audiocassette (Box 3)
  - Pressman, Jeffry, audiocassette (Box 33)
  - Rahe, Paul, interviewed by Brook Manville, transcript only (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Robinson, Ken, 4 audiocassettes (Box 34–37)
  - Rochon, Gilbert, audiocassette (Box 38)
  - Rose, Peter, interviewed by Brook Manville, audiocassette (Box 39)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Schmoke, Kurt, interviewed by Brook Manville, audiocassette (Box 40)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sewall, Richard, audiocassette (Box 41)
  - Slie, Sam, audiocassette (Box 42)
  - Spinrad, Alex, audiocassette (Box 43)
  - Tharp, Charles, audiocassette (Box 44)
  - Thomas, Dean B., audiocassette (Box 45)
  - Thorburn, David, interviewed by David Winn, audiocassette (Box 46)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Triffin, Robert, audiocassette (Box 47)
  - Trinklaus, J. P., audiocassette (Box 48)
  - Warren, David, audiocassette (Box 49)
  - Wilkinson, John, interviewed by Brook Manville, audiocassette (Box 50)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Woodward, C. V., audiocassette (Box 51)
  - Zaeder, Rev. Phillip, interview by Joel Krieger, audiocassette (Box 52)
    - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Transcripts of interviews for which audiorecordings were made (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence concerning the 1970 May Day Strike, Accession 1984-A-069
  - Argyris, Chris (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Belson, Charles V., Jr. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Boell, Edgar (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Brooks, Peter (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bryce-Laporte, Roy S. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cannon, Beekman C. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chauncey, Henry, Jr. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clark, Elias (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Coffin, William S. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Eisenstein, Hester (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Farley, William H. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Fitt, Alfred B. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Frutkin, Ren (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Goldstein, Abraham (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Guida, Mayor Bartholmew F. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hallett, Douglas L. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hirshleifer, John (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Horowitz, William (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Johnson, Gary (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Keniston, Kenneth (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Kernan, Alvin (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Lauber, Albert (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Macchioni, Albert (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - May, Georges (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Morris, James M. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ogilvy, James (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Osborne, Ernest L. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Rahe, Paul (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Rose, Peter (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Samuels, E. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Schmoke, Alexander (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Sewall, Richard (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Slie, Samuel W. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Spinrad, Alexander (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Thomas, Elisabeth (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Thorburne, David (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Triffin, Robert (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Trinkaus, J.P. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Warren, David (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Wilkinson, John (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Zaeder, J. Philip (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Original Quote Sheets A-L (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Original Quote Sheets M-Z (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Materials concerning the 1970 May Day strike, Accession 1988-A-089
  - Printed Material, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Memos to Faculty and Students; Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Materials documenting the Black Panthers and the May Day Rally, 1970; Accession 2003-A-080
  - Statements, releases, students and administration, Circa 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Newspapers regarding rally and the Black Panthers, Circa 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Newspapers regarding rally and the Black Panthers, Circa 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Newspapers regarding Black Panther Party and New Haven Panther Defense Committee, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- May Day "Strikes" tee-shirt made in Berkeley College print shop, 1970; Accession 2003-A-090
  - May Day "Strikes" tee-shirt made in Berkeley College print shop, 1970 (Box 1)
- Black Panther "solidarity" t-shirt, 1970; Accession 2009-A-200
  The materials are open for research.
  - Black Panther "solidarity" t-shirt, 1970 (Box 1)
- Strike Newspaper, 1970 April 23 - May 18; Accession 2010-A-079; 0.02; (1 envelope) (Box 1, Folder 1)
- May Day rally posters, 1970; Accession 2010-A-080; 2.5; (1 folio) (Folder 1)
- Black Panther and Yale-related materials, 1969-1970; Accession 2012-A-028
  - National anti-war activities, Circa 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - National anti-war and student strike publications and brochures, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Anti-war and Black Panther activities-New Haven, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anti-war activities and student strike-Yale, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Anti-war and May Day publications at Yale, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Strike Newspaper"-May Day activities at Yale, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - The Black Panther Black Community News service, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Black Panther publications, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Black Panther statements, ephemera and news clippings, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Black Panther "solidarity" shirt and silk screen banner, 1970; Accession 2014-A-016; 1; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  This accession consists of two items: a button-down shirt silk-screened on the back with the word, "Solidarity," as well as an illustration featuring the Black Panther Party logo and a bulldog; and a blue cloth banner silk screened with two Black Panther Party logos and the phrase, "POLITICAL PRISONERS OF USA FASCISM." Both the shirt and the banner were donated by Karla Forsythe, a 1971 Yale College graduate.
  - Black Panther "solidarity" button-down shirt, 1970 (Box 1)
  - "Political prisoners of U.S.A. fascism" silk screen banner, 1970 (Box 1)
- Letter on the Black Panther trial, 1970 April 21; Accession 2017-A-013
  - Letter on the Black Panther trial, 1970 April 21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Unidentified typescript letter describing the events leading up to, and during the trial of the Black Panthers in New Haven.
- May Day Rally films, 1970-05; Accession 2017-A-041
  This accession contains two short films that document activities from the May Day Rally that took place on the New Haven Green. The films were created by Frank Gardner, a New Haven-based film maker.
  Access to the original film reels is restricted. Researchers must use the available digital surrogates.
  - "May Day Color", 1970-05; 1 (Box 1)
    Color film with no sound. Run time is two minutes and ten seconds.
  - "Skywriter, Black Panthers", 1970-05; 1 (Box 2)
    Color film with no sound. Run time is eight minutes and forty-two seconds.